Guide to the Yale School of Drama Master of Fine Arts Theses
Yale University Arts Library
Yale School of Drama Master of Fine Arts Theses
1942-2015
DRA 28
Yale University Arts Library
18.77
(45 boxes)
This collection contains thesis projects submitted in partial fulfillment for the degree of Master of Fine Arts at the Yale School of Drama.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the authors.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains thesis projects submitted in partial fulfillment for the degree of Master of Fine Arts at the Yale School of Drama.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Directing. II. Stage Management. III. Technical Design and Production. IV. Miscellaneous.
Theater -- Production and direction; Stage management; Theses
- Directing Theses, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes production books from third-year director's thesis projects, in partial fulfillment of requirements for the Master of Fine Arts degree in Directing at the Yale School of Drama.
  Arrangement
  Series is arranged chronologically by year of completion, then alphabetically by author surname within each year.
  - Saint Mac by John Kneubuhl. Production book, with essay, by Virginia H. Mealy, 1942; Mealy, Virginia H. (Box 32)
  - The Inquilines; a play / written and directed by Vincent Park., 1953; Park, Vincent (Box 34)
  - The Government Inspector by Nikolai Gogol. Production book of YSD production Jan/Feb, 1977, Gordon, Denise A. (Box 34)
  - Director's thesis on Euripides' Alcestis., 1978; Preston, Travis (Box 34)
  - Models of life: a director's thesis., 1991; Kramer, Daniel Elihu (Box 34)
  - Happy end: a production casebook / Eleanor Holdridge., 1997; Holdridge, Eleanor (Box 36)
  - The Crazy Locomotive by Stanislaw Ignacy Witkiewicz / directed by Annie Dorsen, 1999; Dorsen, Annie (Box 24)
  - The People vs. The God of Vengeance by Scholem Asch and Rebecca Bayla Taichman / directed by Rebecca Bayla Taichman, 2000; Taichman, Rebecca Bayla (Box 24)
  - The Life and Death of King John by William Shakespeare / directed by Stephen Fried, 2005; Fried, Stephen (Box 28)
  - Hamlet written by William Shakespeare / adapted and directed by May Adrales, 2006; Adrales, May (Box 1)
  - The Duchess of Malfi by John Webster / directed by Susanna Gellert, 2006; Gellert, Susanna (Box 1)
  - Attempts on Her Life by Martin Crimp / directed by Anna Jones, 2006; Jones, Anna (Box 3)
  - Zero Hour / written and directed by Tea Alagic, 2007; Alagic, Tea (Box 2)
  - Baal by Bertolt Brecht / directed by Snehal Desai, 2007; Desai, Snehal (Box 31)
  - Persecution and assassination of Jean-Paul Marat as performed by the inmates of the Asylum of Charenton under the direction of the Marquis of Sade / English version by Geoffrey Skelton Verse adaptation by Adrian Mitchell / directed by Nelson T. Eusebio, III, 2007; Eusebio, Nelson T., III (Box 4)
  - Venus by Suzan-Lori Parks / directed by Jessi D. Hill, 2007; Hill, Jessi D. (Box 5)
  - Peer Gynt by Henrik Ibsen / directed by Mike Donahue, 2008; Donahue, Mike (Box 6)
  - The Ghost Sonata by August Strindberg / directed by Shana Cooper, 2009; Cooper, Shana (Box 3)
  - The Robbers by Friedrich Schiller / directed by Rebecca Wolff, 2009; Wolff, Rebecca (Box 6)
  - La Ronde by Arthur Schnitzler, translated by Carl R. Mueller, 2010; Jou, Jesse Jou, Jesse Yi-Teh (Box 18)
  - Phèdre by Jean Racine, translated by Ted Hughes / directed by Christopher Mirto, 2010; Mirto, Christopher (Box 18)
  - Man=Man by Erik Pearson, 2010; Pearson, Erik (Box 18)
  - Orlando by Sarah Ruhl / directed by Jen Wineman, 2010; Wineman, Jen (Box 28)
  - Eurydice by Jean Anouilh / directed by Devin Brain, 2011; Brain, Devin (Box 28)
  - A Streetcar Named Desire by Tennessee Williams / directed by Charlotte Brathwaite, 2011; Brathwaite, Charlotte (Box 29)
  - Jib by Michael McQuilken / directed by Michael McQuilken, 2011; McQuilken, Michael (Box 29)
  - Doctor Faustus Lights the Lights by Gertrude Stein / directed by Lileana Blain-Cruz, 2012; Blain-Cruz, Lileana (Box 30)
  - The Seagull by Anton Chekov / directed by Alexandru Mihail, 2012; Mihail, Alexandru (Box 30)
  - Cymbeline by William Shakespeare / directed by Louisa Proske, 2012; Proske, Louisa (Box 30)
  - Cloud Nine by Caryl Churchill / directed by Margot Bordelon, 2013; Bordelon, Margot (Box 31)
  - The master and margarita / by Mikhail Bulgakov / adapted by Edward Kemp, directed by Sara Holdren at Yale School of Drama, October 21-25, 2014., Holdren, Sara (Box 45)
  - Friedrich Dürrenmatt's "The Visit" / presented at the Iseman Theater on October 29th through November 2nd 2014., Lewis, Cole (Box 45)
  - Hedda Gabler / director's casebook for Henrik Ibsen's Hedda Gabler presented at the University Theater at Yale School of Drama on February 1-7, 2014., McGerr, Katherine (Box 45)
  - Don Juan / by Molière, translated by Brendan Pelsue, adapted by Andrej Visky, Brendan Pelsue, and Samantha Lazar. Yale School of Drama January 27-31, 2015., Visky, Andrej (Box 45)
- Stage Management Theses, Series II
  This series includes theses by third-year stage managers, in partial fulfillment of requirements for the Master of Fine Arts degree in Stage Management at the Yale School of Drama.
  This series is divided into two subseries: I. Production Theses (acting editions/production books for productions staged); and II. Written Theses (research and critical analysis on a faculty-approved topic in theatre history or practice). Both subseries are arranged chronologically by year of completion, then alphabetically by author surname within each year.
  - Production Theses
    - Sunset crowd / by John Kneubuhl; a production book, 1942; Lande, Anita (Box 33)
    - The Tempest, by William Shakespeare: acting edition., 1974; Harrington, Charlene; 2 (Box 37)
    - Shlemiel the first / by Isaac Bashevis Singer; acting edition by Peter Roberts., 1975; Roberts, Peter, 1925-; 2 (Box 37)
    - Suicide in B-Flat ( A Mysterious Overture) by Sam Shepard: acting edition, 1977; Hershey, Jennifer; 2 volumes (Box 37)
    - Wings by Arthur Kopit: acting edition, 1978; Carbaugh, H. Lloyd; 2 (Box 38)
    - The Mystery Plays by Roberto Aguirre-Sacasa: acting edition, 2004; McCarter, Molly Elizabeth (Box 7)
    - The People Next Door by Henry Adams, 2006; Senavinin, Shawn Brian (Box 7)
    - Black Snow by Mikhail Bulgakov / adapted by Keith Reddin: acting edition, 2007; DiGregorio, Derek Michael (Box 7)
    - Lulu by Frank Wedekind / translated by Carl Mueller / adapted by Mark Lamos and Drew Lichtenberg: acting edition, 2007; Olson, Katrina Lynn (Box 8)
    - The Mistakes Madeline Made by Elizabeth Meriwether: acting edition, 2007; Rossini, Nicola (Box 8)
    - The Evildoers by David Adjmi / directed by Rebecca Taichman, 2008; McInerney, Joanne E. (Box 8)
    - A Woman of No Importance by Oscar Wilde: acting edition, 2008; Olivieri, Sarah (Box 9)
    - Trouble in Mind by Alice Childress / directed by Irene Lewis, 2008; Shuster, Lisa-Marie (Box 9)
    - Notes from Underground by Fyodor Dostoevsky / adapted by Robert Woodruff and Bill Camp: acting edition, 2009; Longley-Postema, Kris (Box 9)
    - Rough Crossing by Tom Stoppard / directed by Mark Rucker: acting edition, 2009; O'Brien, Iris (Box 10)
    - Happy Now? by Lucinda Coxon / directed by Liz Diamond: acting edition, 2009; Spooner, Amanda (Box 10)
    - Compulsion by Rinne Groff / directed by Oskar Eustis: acting edition, 2010; Barker, Jessica (Box 10)
    - Eclipsed by Danai Gurira / directed by Liesl Tommy: acting edition, 2010; Hashley, Karen (Box 11)
  - Written Theses
    - Ruth Gordon, her stage career., 1964; Bretz, Carol (Box 36)
    - Creative Arts Centre for Trinidad and Tobago; A Preliminary Study in Functional Design, 1965; Lyndersay, Dexter (Box 24)
      Box 24 also contains "A Project in Architectural Lighting," which is another work by Lyndersay.
    - The performing arts: a proposed union, by Don S. Anderson., 1969; Anderson, Don S. (Box 38)
    - The case for resident repertory theatre in Denver, Colorado., 1969; Ingram, Mary Jane (Box 38)
    - Additional spaces for existing theatres / by Daniel L. Koetting., 1974; Koetting, Daniel L. (Box 38)
    - Proposed LORT-Equity agreement governing employment in conservatory theatres / Francis A. Lackner., 1974; Lackner, Francis A.; 2 (Box 38)
    - The Theatrical Organization: a systems view / by Charles E. Letts, III., 1976; Letts, Charles E. (Box 39)
    - The Story Keeper: The Evolution of Stage Management in Ancient Greece and Rome, 2010; Sherry, Bree (Box 11)
    - The Relationship Between Stage Manager and Director: Interviews with Professionals in the Field, 2010; Woods, Jenna (Box 11)
- Technical Design and Production Theses, Series III
  This series includes theses by third-year Technical Design and Production students, in partial fulfillment of requirements for the Master of Fine Arts degree in Technical Design and Production at the Yale School of Drama.
  - A Lighting Layout for High School Auditoriums and Stages, 1942; Kleiner, Anne May (Box 23)
  - Stage Lighting in the Opera House, 1948; Dace, Wallace (Box 23)
  - Dramatic Production in the Private, Secondary Schools of Connecticut, 1948; Smith, Harvey K. (Box 23)
  - A Graphic Survey of Stage Lighting, vol. I-II, 1952; Allison, Walter H. (Box 11)
  - Unistrut Theatre Architecture, A Use Study, 1957; Locklin, David (Box 12)
  - Optics for the Theatre Technician, 1963; Price, Michael P. (Box 23)
  - Light and the Music Drama: The Aesthetic Basis and Technical Practice of Stage Lighting at the Bayreuth Festspielhaus, 1964; Lucas, John Robert (Box 23)
  - The portable stage light simulator, by Daniel H. Proctor., 1970; Proctor, Daniel H. (Box 39)
  - Lighting and Sound Systems for the Swimming Pool of the Northfield School, 1970; Waaser, Carol M. (Box 24)
  - Characteristics of the Yale Spotline Winch, by Craig T. Martin., 1971; Martin, Craig T. (Box 39)
  - The history and technology of pre-electric theatre lighting., 1973; Penzel, Frederick, 1948- (Box 39)
  - Production problems in regional theaters, Part I, by Kathryn M. Pinner., 1973; Pinner, Kathryn M. (Box 43)
  - The Yale Drama Inventory Management System: A Computer Based Inventory System For Non-Profit Institutions, 1974; Lindsay, George (Box 40)
  - Acoustical design: Yale Repertory Theatre renovation 1975 / by Mitchell Kurtz., Kurtz, Mitchell (Box 40)
  - Modelling basic operating overhead in theatre buildings: a pilot study at three universities / submitted by Jonathan Seth Miller., 1975; Miller, Jonathan Seth (Box 42)
  - Theater rigging: a guide to maintenance inspection / by Thomas J. Kupp., 1976; Kupp, Thomas J. (Box 40)
  - A hydraulic primer for theatre production personnel / by Andrew J. Kufta., 1977; Kufta, Andrew J. (Box 40)
  - Management for the technical manager / by William J. Reynolds., 1977; Reynolds, William J. (Box 41)
  - Stress-skin panel design / by Robert C. Heller., 1978; Heller, Robert C. (Box 41)
  - Fire protection for scenery / by Pamela Ann Martindell., 1978; Martindell, Pamela Ann (Box 41)
  - Safety in the theatre: a study of safety in ten university/college theatres in the New England area / by Cosmo A. Catalano., 1979; Catalano, Cosmo A. (Box 41)
  - A new recommended practice for reporting photometric performance of theatrical lighting instruments / by Jane C. Head., 1979; Head, Jane C. (Box 41)
  - Stage light color media analysis using photoelectric colorimetry / by Walter R. Klappert., 1979; Klappert, Walter R. (Box 42)
  - An introduction to structural engineering for the technical director / by Arthur I. Rank, III., 1979; Rank, Arthur I. (Box 42)
  - The YRT Motion Control System, 1998; Bellber, Joseph (Box 25)
  - Design of Structural Plates for Theatre, 2005; Corbett, Kimberly (Box 12)
  - Designing a Theatrical Hydraulic Scissor Lift, 2005; Hood, Guerry (Box 12)
  - Motor-Drives for Turntables, 2005; Lin, Lung-Kuei (Box 12)
  - Planar Truss Design and Construction for Theatre, 2005; Wells, Nathaniel (Box 12)
  - Production Planning Database for Technical Directors: Ashomen, 2006; Bollinger, Aaron (Box 13)
  - Introduction to Video Image Systems for Regional Theatre Productions, 2006; Culligan, Sean (Box 19)
  - Reasons for Producing Special Events: An Examination of Selected West Coast Regional Theatres, 2006; Eldredge, Janann (Box 13)
  - A Theatrical Hand Winch for Scenic Motion, 2006; Farrow, Andrew Stephen (Box 13)
  - Aluminum Structural Design for the Stage, 2006; Powers, Bradley L. (Box 13)
  - The Use of Hydraulic Accumulators in Theatrical Hydraulic Systems, 2006; Winkler, Greg (Box 13)
  - Deck Tracks in the Commercial Theatre, 2007; Banta, Michael D. (Box 13)
  - The Safe Use, Storage, Handling, and Maintenance of Handguns: A Manual for Theatre Production Staff, 2007; Calica, David (Box 13)
  - The Way Technical Theatre Systems Work, 2007; Carlson, Gregg (Box 14)
  - LED Displays as an Alternative to Projections for the Stage, 2007; Dahl, Adam J. (Box 14)
  - YSDSM User Manual, 2007; Durham, Ryan C. (Box 14)
  - Wide-Format Digital Printing for the Stage, 2007; Hamlin, Joseph (Box 14)
  - The Place of Theater Programs in Private Secondary Schools in New England, 2007; Krier, Kathryn (Box 14)
  - African Americans in Technical Theater: Paths to Follow, 2007; Peterson, Moshe Hotseanyu Ben-Yehudah (Box 14)
  - Productivity Applications in AutoCAD, 2008; Neuenschwander, Steven (Box 14)
  - A Touchscreen-Based Motion Control System for Theatre, 2008; Peterson, Christopher M. (Box 15)
  - Making the Move to Moving Lights, 2008; Reed, Jonathan A. (Box 15)
  - From Page to Stage: A Guide to Documenting and Managing a Production's Property Needs, 2008; Stark, Ben (Box 15)
  - An Advanced Motion Control Demonstrator, 2008; Willis, Jonathan (Box 15)
  - Across the Pacific Ocean: A Guide to Performing Musicals in Korea, 2008; Yang, HaeWon (Box 15)
  - An Introduction to Stage Machinery Components, 2009; Buckhurst, Colin (Box 19)
  - An Undergraduate Course in Lighting Design, 2009; Delgado, Thomas R. (Box 19)
  - Introducing SketchUp for Theater Applications, 2009; Eo, Kyoung-jun (Box 19)
  - ACN Lighting Networks: A Guide to Current Uses and Possible Future Trends of ANSI E1.17, ASN, 2009; Furmanek, Joel (Box 19)
  - Plumbing for the Stage: A Technician's Handbook, 2009; Gitchel, Andrew James (Box 19)
  - 4 Axes Positioning Unit (4APU): Use and Construction Manual v.1.0, 2009; Hourclé, Chris (Box 25)
  - Motor Control Fundamentals, 2009; Lisowski, Daniel T. (Box 25)
  - Jigs and Fixtures for the Scene Shop, 2009; McCullough, John (Box 19)
  - OSHA's Hazard Communication Standard: A Reference Guide to Compliance for the Technical Manager, 2009; Southard, Andrew F. (Box 20)
  - An Introduction to AutoCad VBA Programming for the Technical Manager, 2009; Twining, Lily (Box 20)
  - A Regional Theater Production Manager's Guide to Key Issues in Federal Employment Law, 2009; Vandercook, Michael (Box 20)
  - LEED Certification of Performing Arts Buildings, 2009; Welander, Matthew T. (Box 20)
  - Electromechanical Splined Hub Spring Set Brakes: A Reference Manual, 2010; Berendes, David (Box 20)
  - 3D AutoCad: A Guide for Theatre Draftspersons, 2010; Brown, Chris (Box 20)
  - A Planning Primer and Case Studies in the Design and Construction of High School Performing Arts Centers, 2010; Kraczek, Michael S. (Box 20)
  - Compound Angles for Scenery Construction, 2010; Malbuisson, Peter A. (Box 21)
  - Analyzing the Utility of Web-Based Project Management Services Within Regional Theater Production Management, 2010; Retartha, Ryan (Box 21)
  - Scenic Construction for Taiwan, 2010; Sun, Tien-Yin (Box 21)
  - Batteries for Theatrical Effects: A Quick Reference Guide for Technical Designers, 2010; Sunderman, Erik Michael (Box 21)
  - Power-Line Communications Performance Testing and Verification, 2010; Swetcky, Christopher (Box 21)
  - Applying ESTA Draft BSR E1.6-1--201X, Entertainment-Powered Hoist Systems to a Practical Project. An Example of How the Standard Will Affect the Design of Regional Theatre Hoists, 2011; Becker, Andrew (Box 21)
  - Wireless Three-Dimensional Positioning Technologies for Theatrical Use, 2011; Bolton, Erich (Box 21)
  - A Hydraulic Destructive Test Stand, 2011; Dambacher, Brian D. (Box 25)
  - Observations on Current Theatre Safety, and Safety Training and Implementation in Estonia., 2011; Hales, Ryan Christopher (Box 21)
  - Props Master: A Database System for Properties Management., 2011; Henson, Stephen C. (Box 22)
  - Occupational Certification for the Entertainment Technician., 2011; Merrick, Benjamin W. (Box 22)
  - Chain Hoists: A Theatrical User's Guide., 2011; Starmer, John Barrett (Box 22)
  - An Overview of CNC Waterjet Cutting for the Stage., 2011; Tharp, Katherine Gloria (Box 22)
  - Theatrical Turntables., 2011; Zwicky, James (Box 22)
  - Negotiating Collaboration: An Introduction to Interest-Based Negotiation Techniques for New Technical Managers., 2012; Amarakoon, Shaminda (Box 25)
  - An Investigation of Production Management in Taiwan., 2012; Chen, Hsiao-Ya (Box 25)
  - User Interface Design for Scenery Control Systems., 2012; Graboyes, Shaina (Box 25)
  - A Handbook of Period Styles., 2012; Wicker, Kate (Box 25)
  - Incorporating solar power into theatre: a case study., 2012; Russo, Christopher S. (Box 26)
  - Accounting and reporting software for the Production Manager., 2012; Stoltman, Joseph Aaron (Box 26)
  - What every TD needs to know about live sound: (and nothing more), 2013; Backhaus, Michael Frederick (Box 44)
  - Fire retarding: codes, process, & administration., 2013; Casanova, Eric C. (Box 26)
  - 3D drafting for theater: a guide to drawing and layer management., 2013; Griffith, Theodore Barrett (Box 26)
  - An introduction to digital video software and media for live productions., 2013; Hilley, John F. (Box 26)
  - Projection engineering handbook: vol. 1 hardware., 2013; Lin, Eric Chi-Yeh (Box 26)
  - Platform and decking systems., 2013; McDaniel, Justin (Box 26)
  - International shipping for the entertainment industry: a guide for the technical manager., 2013; McNally, Kellen C. (Box 26)
  - A practical approach to designing a multiuser database application., 2013; Pellow, Jonathan (Box 26)
  - Understanding the dynamics of theater structures., 2013; Perez, Daniel (Box 27)
  - Increasing productivity through employee wellness., 2013; Smallwood, Brian Macinnis (Box 27)
  - A practical handbook: basic stage electricity and wiring., 2013; Swanson, Brian (Box 27)
  - The technical theatre training programme in Esplanade: theatres on the Bay, Singapore: a model for professional practice in the Philippines., 2013; Tan-Tiongco, Maree Barbara (Box 27)
  - The inter-related pendulum system., 2013; Verdery, Aaron (Box 27)
  - A code compliance handbook for small theatres in New York City., 2013; Walcott, Karen (Box 27)
  - Video switching for corporate events: staging techniques international's HD video switching system., 2014; Albert, Steven (Box 35)
  - An introduction to stage automation for the artistic team, 2014; Anderson, Kaitlyn E. (Box 44)
  - Electrical safety: a standards based approach for the entertainment electrician., 2014; Bennett, Justin (Box 35)
  - 3D printing: a guide for technical theatre managers., 2014; Bergeron, Alex (Box 35)
  - An examination of theatre staffing for projection engineering., 2014; Bromley, Nicole (Box 35)
  - An overview of EtherCAT-Based automation systems by Beckhoff., 2014; Christiani, Nicholas (Box 35)
  - Stress analysis in autodesk inventor for theatrical technical designers, 2014; Groeneveld, Matthew Wilson (Box 44)
  - How to design a sunroof: a guide for the technical manager, 2014; Keryczynskyj, Christina (Box 44)
  - Use of wireless networking in automation control systems., 2014; Michael, Samual A. (Box 35)
  - The green scene: a study of environmental sustainability at LORT Member Theaters., 2014; Mills, Courtney Nicole (Box 35)
  - Structural steel design for the stage., 2014; Schmidt, Steven A. (Box 35)
  - Reverse engineered counterweight assist winch by Sanghun Joung, 2015; Joung, Sanghun (Box 44)
- Miscellaneous, Series IV
  - Academic Theatres in the United States, 1930-1943., 1946; Quinby, George H.; 4 (Box 16)
  - Monte Cristo by Alexander Dumas / adapted by Charles Fechter and James O'Neill, 1948; Schoenhut, George W. (Box 17)
  - Symbiosis: a project for Yale [by] Ibel, McHose [and] Michaelis., 1969; Michaelis, Donald; Ibel, Manfred; McHose, T. J. (Box 42)
  - The Stanford Repertory Theatre; notes on professional theatre and the university., 1969; McHose, Janet (Box 42)
  - A chronicle of the Yale Repertory Theatre film project / by Matthew Krashan., 1977; Krashan, Matthew (Box 42)